Hi, we've seen all the curves and splines I wanted to cover in this video series.
Now there is one thing I want to do with all those curves is that every time I showed you
the curves it was actually in a 2D curve.
So every point has x and y coordinate, x and y coordinate and then the parameterization
of the curve itself was a T that was moving inside of that 2D space.
It could have been a 3D space,
so it could have been a curve going through a 3D world,
would have been exactly the same mathematics.
Now, if we want to use those curves
to actually encode animation data,
what we have to do is go down to a one-dimensional curve.
And what I mean by that is that usually,
if you encode animation data, you will do keyframes.
So, you know, you have a timeline
and each few frames you give a value
and then you try to interpolate those values.
So that's how usually you see basic curves use,
the helmet curve use inside of Maya or that kind of stuff.
Now, the mathematic for those might be a bit different
than the 2D case.
So I will cover each case and show you what we can do
and how we can compute a 1D example
to actually have key frames data.
So if you go one dimensional spline,
The first thing we can do is go with the Amid Curve.
And a one-dimensional Amid Curve,
which actually means the bottom line
so that my X's will be actually my T,
so it will be the T that I usually go through the curves,
and I get the value as Y.
Now, the Amid Curves goes between zero and one,
and one thing I can do if it's only two keyframes.
So what I have here is my keyframes are separate
in key times and key values.
So my key times is four and 25,
my key values is four and two.
And so I get the tangent that was normally decided
for the curve.
And if I render this, basically what happened now
is that I have really my frames
and I've plotted the values that I would get
if I was requesting the value at each frame.
So I had the keyframe data at my frame four and 26.
Oh, it was four and 25, sorry, four and 25.
And then that's my curve
and you get everything here working properly.
To get this to work,
what I did actually is to assume
that the Armit curve would be a value of size of one.
And so I compute it as a size of one
and then I scale up the value.
so I can reach it.
The only thing you have to do is that
if you take your range and you actually scale it,
what happens, the tangent you had
would actually stays the same
and so the curve will start to get flat.
So the only thing you have to do is that
knowing that you scaled your range,
say that's my range here,
between the two, I use that range
to multiply my tangent.
So actually I compensate for the fact
that I will be stretching the curve I'm computing.
So that's how you could do it for one single army curve.
It's fairly easy to do.
Just remember that you basically stretch your functions.
So you actually have to stretch your tangent also.
If we go one step further
and we go toward the cardinal spline,
we will have to do that same kind of concept,
but there is a few tweak in there.
If I go uniform cardinal spline meaning that every key frame every key time will
be the same range between them so you know my key time here is 4, 8, 12, 16 so it's
on a regular grid. I could do the same trick as the one I did for the
Hermit curve. I can compute my cardinal spline and I can just stretch it. Now
Now, because the cardinal spline already computes the tensions and the curve, for me in this
case, I don't even need to bother about tension because when you go one dimension, basically
that tension factor is useless.
You cannot ask your cardinal spline to be linear or curved when you do one dimensional.
You can only tweak the y values and the t is assumed to be regular under the hood.
So the tension has no meaning.
And so if I do this, basically I compute the kernel spline as if it was just, you know,
a kernel spline that was going from one to four, just linear steps inside of my animation.
I compute the curves, and then I can stretch it
because the tension has already been computed,
the curves have already been computed.
I don't need to do anything else
than just stretching the end results.
Basically, actually, I'm not doing a stretch.
I'm just stepping through it as if it was a stretch.
So again, cardinal spline,
if you are regular inside of a cardinal spline,
then you can actually get the values for each frame
just by requesting the value properly.
Now if you go non-uniform cardinal spline,
then you try to do the same thing,
showing I take my entire cardinal spline
and then compute it and try to stretch it.
What will happen is basically this.
My curve will not go through the points
if it was really set up on the keyframes.
It would assume that actually my T is linear
And so my T will be, I assume that my frame is here
and my frame is there.
So I cannot just do a complete stretch
of the final result.
What I need to do instead is actually use the fact
that I can do the Amid curve and I can stretch Amid curve.
So I can reuse my functions that I had before,
which was the one that converts the Carnival splines
into a bunch of Hermit and so I could do that calling the cardinal spline having
the Hermit points and then for each range I can properly stretch them the same way
as I did it for the example of the Hermit just by restretching the the
tangents for each of the range I'm computing and now I have something that
looks correct with all my different tangents and I get the values that
actually on the curve every time when I requested a keyframe. Okay? The next one
is doing a basic curve. Again a basic curve of one dimensional might be a bit
weird but then we could do the uniform basic curve meaning that I will have you
know one basic curve is four points and so I have my four points properly
spaced on my timeline so I get again my 481216 to represent my points and if I
do this I can properly compute a Bezier curve that is actually a
one-dimensional so I get my my T's down here and I get my values that go there
now you might notice that when we go uniform Bezier curve it also means that
my keyframes are really you know my first keyframe is at time zero my second one is at time one third
my third one two third and my final one is at one remember when we did the conversion from
bezier curve to amit curve we had to divide the tension by three that's one of the hints that's
why we have to do it is because a uniform bezier curve basically has a split in four parts
So it's 0, 1, 3, 2, 3, and 1.
So it works if you really put all your points
along those values.
Now, if you were trying to do non-niform basic curves,
I would have the same issues as the cardinal.
It would just compute something that makes no sense.
So there is actually only one way
to do a basic curve that you could sample to get keyframes.
And that's how every animation package are doing it,
is that for this specific case,
you actually do a 2D base year curve.
So instead of having my time at the bottom and my value,
what you will have is a 2D base year curve
that will be time value together.
And then we have to find a way to sample that properly
to get the value we wanted for each frame.
And that's what we call usually the finding y given x.
I would first probably execute the example
and then we can explain what's happening
because it will be easier in this way.
So when we do a basic of the t values
that goes between them does not represent
a linear time in my timeline.
So the t value here is not continuous compared to all the keyframe I'm trying to reach.
So the thing we have to do is actually try to find the opposite, asking if I want to
be to a specific keyframe value, what would be the t parameters of my curve I need to
use for that curve to actually be on that spot.
And how we do this is by doing the mapping between t and the time, the real time.
So I get my t value that goes between 0 and 1.
And I get my real time that goes between 4 and 16.
So that's the time that comes here.
And I get the t down here.
And so what you have to do is say, if I wanted to be at frame 10 in my timing here, if I want
to be at frame 10, I need to be here and I need to be able to find the t value that
represents my frame 10 and see it's not 0.5 because this is not just a linear mapping.
And how you do this is basically realizing that this graph here, when we ask for what
the T there is the same as moving that graph up and down and then trying to find the roots.
So usually finding the roots mean finding where this curve will hit zero. That's how you find a
root. And so what you need to do is to say I want to take the entire curve that was drawn as usual.
I want to shift it down 10 frames because I'm looking for frame 10. And then as soon as I've
I've shifted down, I can find my root,
and I can know that it will be hitting here
nearly something 0.4 or something, right?
So that's what mathematically we do.
And that's what this function is doing.
It takes the time at which you actually want
to evaluate for t, and it computes the basic curve
with that little minus time I'm looking for.
And then it finds the roots.
I'm using the root function from NumPy.
It's a cubic function,
so you can have more than one root.
I know that I'm constraining the system,
so I can only have one root or zero
if I'm outside of my animation.
But if I'm inside of my animation,
I constrain the curve itself
to not give me more than one root,
so I can just return the first root that will be valid.
And to understand what's happening here and how we could we compute this it's basically because
If I do it with same pie again to go through the mathematics
If I start with the bezier function as usual, so that's the the bezier
Compute it with the Bernstein basis function
If I expand it all that's how you compute the entire
function now based on x0 x1 x2 x3 and so on and I know that the thing I want to
do is move it's basically taking the points you have here so I get my four
points here and to move this up and down what I will do is actually I would
shift the entire all the points here I would shift it on the side to actually
try to bring that 10 right here, right?
So what I'm doing now is I will keep the mathematics that
actually compute the Bayesian curve.
And I will say that I want to shift the entire Bayesian curve
using a substitute.
So I replace the x0 by x0 minus x1 is x1 minus x and so on.
And that gives you that massive functions
now, where every x0 is x0 minus x, x1 is x1 minus x and so on and so on and so on.
And if I try to ask him to factorize that and re rearrange it, you will see that every x
cancel each other except the last one. So you only have one minus x. So you could keep the
entire functions as is and just do a minus x at the end and that's the beauty of doing it this way
and that's what you have here basically when I find the roots I find the root for a cubic function
that is a b c d and it's just the d that has the minus x here so that's how we actually do it for
a basic curve it's a bit more involved a bit more complex but I tell you to have a 2d curve
and to sample it linearly through your time.
That's how it's completed usually.
And the final thing I want to show you
because it might be useful is good to be able
to represent your animation data
using one type of curves and that kind of stuff.
One thing we might need to do at some point
is actually encode your animation data.
So it might come from a really massive array
of data and you just want to fit a curve through it and encode a curve that represents your animation
data that has heavily as what you have as input. And so what I would do here is actually fit a
uniform cubic B spline using the minimize system from NumPy or SimPy. I don't remember
which then where the minimize come from it comes from let me see minimize come from sci-pi sorry
sci-pi optimize and so what i would have is basically a function and i will draw on the
the annual results, that would be easier. So I have a function that is my orange dots.
And that's the function that I would say I want to encode using cubic B spline. And
I get all the points I want to use, the number of points I want to use for my cubic B spline.
And that's where they will be placed. And I get the cubic B spline, which is the one
I've computed that's how my animation would be rendered if I was using it. So I'm fairly close
to my original data and how you do this kind of stuff is basically by having okay I have my
function itself which is now a really complex function that I compute and then I would say
how many points on that curve I would use to try to
encode my data and I said that I would take 20 points around it. I get my B-spline basis,
so again I'm using the formula for the matrix for the B-spline. I have my function to compute
my B-spline and what I would do is I would have a bunch of points. So that's how many
points I want to use on my B-spline. I would say I want to use seven points. And finally,
I get the real value of my function. So I sample my function, as I said, 20 times between every
points so that's my it's all the points on the time and that's the values of my complex function
for all those x's so I take 100 points on my x and I compute the y values for those so I have
an x y values for all of those points and I have an error function that would just be a square error
sum of squares. So I will get my points and inputs. So that's really the control points
of my b-spline. I compute my b-spline with it and then I do the sum of the squares error between
the two. So it's the usual functions you use to minimize an error. You have to start with
an initial guess. So my initial guess is to actually put my points on the curves,
to put my control points on the curves and then I call the minimize with my
error functions and my initial guess and the results itself will give me
where I want that x to be. So my result is here and I get my
optimal y value and then and now that I have the
optimal y values for all of my points I can draw my b-spline so I can
actually display it. That's how you get this kind of stuff. So
it's an optimal uniform cubic B-spline meaning that if I give 20 control points
they will all be spaced with the same space between them if you get only four
that kind of stuff it's a uniform one so you're gonna have more range and
more points in one range and less in the other range is really uniform
but that's how in a nutshell how you would do
fitting a curve and any type of spline. If you have a different type of spline that you
actually want to fit, it would be the same concept. You would use the minimize and try
to find the minimal error. That would be the simplest way to do it, thanks to SciPy.
And I hope this would make sense for later papers when I will start to use these kind
functions and we'll be able to come back to these videos if you ever need to dig a bit deeper into
the curves I'm using at some point. I hope you enjoyed it and see you next time!